<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.7">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-08-08T15:47:42-07:00</updated><id>https://www.deeperwisdom.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Deeper Wisdom</title><subtitle>Welcome to www.DeeperWisdom.org &lt;br /&gt; Stay tuned for resources on the world's wisdom traditions!</subtitle><entry><title type="html">My Course is Live!</title><link href="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/neurophenomenology/2021/06/21/unlocking.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Course is Live!" /><published>2021-06-21T14:47:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-06-21T14:47:00-07:00</updated><id>https://www.deeperwisdom.org/neurophenomenology/2021/06/21/unlocking</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/neurophenomenology/2021/06/21/unlocking.html">&lt;p&gt;My course &lt;a href=&quot;https://udemy.com/course/unlocking-the-unconscious/?referralCode=381E3E4A4AD17989CFD7&quot;&gt;Unlocking the Unconscious through Ritual and Symbol&lt;/a&gt; is now live on Udemy! It covers much of what I’ve been writing about these last two months, but with much more, including exercises and further resources. I hope you’ll check it out!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="neurophenomenology" /><summary type="html">My course Unlocking the Unconscious through Ritual and Symbol is now live on Udemy! It covers much of what I’ve been writing about these last two months, but with much more, including exercises and further resources. I hope you’ll check it out!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Brain as Storyteller</title><link href="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/neurophenomenology/2021/06/07/storyteller.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Brain as Storyteller" /><published>2021-06-07T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-06-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://www.deeperwisdom.org/neurophenomenology/2021/06/07/storyteller</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/neurophenomenology/2021/06/07/storyteller.html">&lt;p&gt;In the mid-20th century, some folks with intractable epilepsy underwent a heroic surgery to separate the two halves of the brain by cutting the corpus callosum. What was remarkable was that, at first, nothing seemed very different about them. But after interviewing them, some clever researchers came up with some interesting experiments to see what had changed. One experiment in particular tells us a lot about how we construct our sense of self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this experiment, the person with the split brain was shown two images: one to the left hemisphere, and one to the right. Remember: the left hemisphere is responsible for language. Also, each hemisphere controls the opposite side of the body. So the right hemisphere controls the left hand. The person was shown a chicken foot and a snowy field to the left and right hemispheres respectively. They were asked to pick what went with what they saw. The right hemisphere, seeing the snowy field, directed the left hand to point to a snow shovel. They were asked why they picked that. The left hemisphere, controlling language, having seen the chicken foot and their left hand picking the snow shovel (but NOT the snowy field) said, without hesitation: “to clean out the chicken shed.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They did not say, “I don’t know,” or “that’s strange.” The brain &lt;em&gt;immediately&lt;/em&gt; came up with a story to explain its behavior. &lt;em&gt;This is what it does all the time.&lt;/em&gt; This is not pathological behavior. This is how the brain normally works.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="neurophenomenology" /><summary type="html">In the mid-20th century, some folks with intractable epilepsy underwent a heroic surgery to separate the two halves of the brain by cutting the corpus callosum. What was remarkable was that, at first, nothing seemed very different about them. But after interviewing them, some clever researchers came up with some interesting experiments to see what had changed. One experiment in particular tells us a lot about how we construct our sense of self.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Time is a Helix</title><link href="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/magick/2021/06/06/time.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Time is a Helix" /><published>2021-06-06T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-06-06T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://www.deeperwisdom.org/magick/2021/06/06/time</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/magick/2021/06/06/time.html">&lt;p&gt;Time is both linear and circular. It’s linear in that there’s a beginning, a middle, and an end. You’re born, you live, you die. It’s circular in that along with this linearity, we also experience periodic cycles, from day to year, and onward to generations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As industrialized humans, we tend to focus on the linear dimension. We are more interested in how the future will be different from the past than in how it will be the same. But for most of human history, the opposite was true. While the rate of linear change has increased exponentially, the circular dimension remains the dimension that connects us to the non-human.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cycles of nature, especially the solar cycles, have a sort of holographic quality. The macro is reflected in the micro. Every day is like a mini year. Dawn is spring, noon is summer, dusk is autumn, and midnight is winter. Every life goes through the same cycle. This can be represented in space according to the relative direction of the Sun. Where the Sun rises (in the East) represents Spring and birth. The Sun at mid-day (South in the Northern hemisphere) is youth. Where the Sun sets (West) is middle age. And where the Sun is hidden (North in the Northern hemisphere) is death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Associating these archetypal forms with their directions is useful in working with them. For example, when working with something new, face the East. When working with the threshold of death, face the Northwest.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="magick" /><summary type="html">Time is both linear and circular. It’s linear in that there’s a beginning, a middle, and an end. You’re born, you live, you die. It’s circular in that along with this linearity, we also experience periodic cycles, from day to year, and onward to generations.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why and How to Read the Bible</title><link href="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/religion/2021/05/27/bible.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why and How to Read the Bible" /><published>2021-05-27T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-05-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://www.deeperwisdom.org/religion/2021/05/27/bible</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/religion/2021/05/27/bible.html">&lt;p&gt;The first time I read the Bible was in 2008. I wasn’t Christian (hadn’t been for two decades) and had recently decided I was an atheist. It just seemed like something any well-educated person should do. I had known some fundamentalists, and they seemed to think the Bible should be read with no mediation or interpretation, so that was how I approached it. Big mistake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bible, and any sacred text for that matter, needs context. There is no way to make sense of it otherwise. What I didn’t realize at the time was that those fundamentalists brought their own context. By the time they read the Bible, they already “knew” how to interpret it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for why, it’s not just about being well-educated. It’s much more than that. There is no part of this Earth that has not been influenced by what’s written in the Bible, especially if you speak English. We all know about Adam and Eve and Noah’s Ark and the 10 Commandments (even if we can’t remember what they are) and even if we don’t know, they affect us nonetheless. It is in our culture, and therefore in our dreams, affecting us in ways that we can scarcely imagine. So part of coming to terms with our own unconscious must include a critical reading of the Bible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But don’t read it without commentary. I recommend &lt;em&gt;the New Oxford Annotated Bible&lt;/em&gt;. And be sure to read the introductory essays and footnotes. Otherwise you’ll just get lost.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="religion" /><summary type="html">The first time I read the Bible was in 2008. I wasn’t Christian (hadn’t been for two decades) and had recently decided I was an atheist. It just seemed like something any well-educated person should do. I had known some fundamentalists, and they seemed to think the Bible should be read with no mediation or interpretation, so that was how I approached it. Big mistake.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Divination is not Fortune Telling</title><link href="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/magick/2021/05/26/divination.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Divination is not Fortune Telling" /><published>2021-05-26T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-05-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://www.deeperwisdom.org/magick/2021/05/26/divination</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/magick/2021/05/26/divination.html">&lt;p&gt;How is divination different from fortune telling? Diviners and fortune tellers both use the same tools (especially tarot), but in very different ways. Fortune tellers claim to be able to tell you the future. They make statistically informed guesses and measure your reaction. Since most people who go to a fortune teller want to believe, they will tend to focus on what the fortune teller gets “right” and forget what they get wrong. For fortune tellers, tarot cards are merely props.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Divination is quite different. The purpose of divination is to get in touch with the divine. In my last post, I described the gods as aspects of the self or the unconscious that transcend the ego. They are the faces on vast psychic powers that we can scarcely comprehend. When I say “psychic,” I simply mean that they exist in the psyche, not that they are in any way supernatural. But they are nonetheless real from a phenomenological point of view. Furthermore, they often know things you (your ego) do not. This is where divination comes in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Divination is a set of techniques whereby we can access that wisdom through the language of symbols. The oldest and most organic form of divination is dream interpretation. Other forms of divination are essentially methods by which to construct what are essentially waking dreams for the purpose of interpretation. They also provide the ability to generate a sort of shared dream with another person to help them access their own divine wisdom.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="magick" /><summary type="html">How is divination different from fortune telling? Diviners and fortune tellers both use the same tools (especially tarot), but in very different ways. Fortune tellers claim to be able to tell you the future. They make statistically informed guesses and measure your reaction. Since most people who go to a fortune teller want to believe, they will tend to focus on what the fortune teller gets “right” and forget what they get wrong. For fortune tellers, tarot cards are merely props.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What are gods?</title><link href="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/magick/2021/05/25/godds.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What are gods?" /><published>2021-05-25T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-05-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://www.deeperwisdom.org/magick/2021/05/25/godds</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/magick/2021/05/25/godds.html">&lt;p&gt;Cultures from all over the world have concepts of non-human intelligences that sometimes interact with the human world. They may be godds, faeries, dæmons, devas, angels, spirits, djinn, &lt;em&gt;etc.&lt;/em&gt; It is remarkable both how widespread this is and also how little conformity there is between how they appear in different cultures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we cannot rule out the possibility that such beings literally exist, I have yet to see convincing evidence that they do. What definitely does exist, however, are aspects of the mind that appear independent of egoic thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If “&lt;a href=&quot;/religion/2021/05/24/god.html&quot;&gt;God&lt;/a&gt;” is the source of the mystery of all existence, we might also call this “the Real.” Then perhaps “the gods” are “the Imaginary.” But being imaginary, they are nonetheless useful and powerful, perhaps even more than “God.” The gods, saints, angels, and even heros, personify forces in our unconscious that can affect us in powerful ways without us even realizing it. And for this reason, it can be useful to engage with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an exercise, try making an altar to a god, angel, saint, or hero. Don’t worry about whether or not it is “real”. But do try to make it beautiful. As you do so, pay attention to how this deity may appear to you. Perhaps you will notice the name of the deity in places you wouldn’t expect. Or messages may appear to you. Don’t worry about whether there really is something “out there.” Just open yourself to communication from that aspect of yourself.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="magick" /><summary type="html">Cultures from all over the world have concepts of non-human intelligences that sometimes interact with the human world. They may be godds, faeries, dæmons, devas, angels, spirits, djinn, etc. It is remarkable both how widespread this is and also how little conformity there is between how they appear in different cultures.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is God?</title><link href="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/religion/2021/05/24/god.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is God?" /><published>2021-05-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-05-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://www.deeperwisdom.org/religion/2021/05/24/god</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/religion/2021/05/24/god.html">&lt;p&gt;In his book &lt;em&gt;21 Lessons for the 21st Century&lt;/em&gt;, Yuval Noah Harari identifies two definitions of God: 1) the source of the mystery of all existence, and 2) a cosmic judge. To monotheists, these two are one and the same. But, Harari argues, equating the two is confusing at best, deceptive at worst. Deceptive because, according to him, monotheists will cite the first definition in trying to refute atheists. Then, once you accept that argument, they say, “see, so you should agree that homosexuals are damned.” Harari, an atheist, posits that it is improper to use the word “God” for meaning 1, as it leads to confusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this last point, I disagree with Harari. The word “God” has a kind of power, like it or not, and we can go further faster if we claim that power rather than work around it. Perhaps you find that you cannot use the word “God” in that way, it has just too many negative connotations. Perhaps you were raised in a fundamentalist family and found liberation in rejecting “God”. Or perhaps you were raised in an atheist family and learned to associate the word “God” with all that is ignorant in humankind. If this is the case, I beg your forgiveness, for I will continue using the word “God” as it suits me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the second definition above, the cosmic judge, I see that as &lt;a href=&quot;/magick/2021/05/25/godds.html&quot;&gt;a&lt;/a&gt; god (lowercase ‘g’), an archetype in the psychological sense. Powerful, though not exactly real.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="religion" /><summary type="html">In his book 21 Lessons for the 21st Century, Yuval Noah Harari identifies two definitions of God: 1) the source of the mystery of all existence, and 2) a cosmic judge. To monotheists, these two are one and the same. But, Harari argues, equating the two is confusing at best, deceptive at worst. Deceptive because, according to him, monotheists will cite the first definition in trying to refute atheists. Then, once you accept that argument, they say, “see, so you should agree that homosexuals are damned.” Harari, an atheist, posits that it is improper to use the word “God” for meaning 1, as it leads to confusion.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is Enlightenment?</title><link href="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/magick/2021/05/23/enlightenment.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is Enlightenment?" /><published>2021-05-23T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-05-23T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://www.deeperwisdom.org/magick/2021/05/23/enlightenment</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/magick/2021/05/23/enlightenment.html">&lt;p&gt;There is an ongoing debate between schools that believe that enlightenment happens suddenly; and those who believe it happens gradually, over a long period of study and practice. As is often the case, both are correct, but in different ways. Sudden enlightenment refers to a change in &lt;em&gt;state&lt;/em&gt; while gradual enlightenment refers to a change in &lt;em&gt;stage&lt;/em&gt; of development. Both are important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first experience of non-dual awareness happened suddenly; not meditating or praying, but while studying cognitive psychology in a café. I had been on this path for only a year. It remains my most memorable mystical experience. I had a realization of oneness with all consciousness. It could not have happened if not for the study and practice which I had been performing. But what happened after that? “Before enlightenment, chop wood, carry water. After enlightenment, chop wood, carry water.” On one level, everything changes, on another level, nothing changes at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is between those two levels? This is where the gradual approach comes in. It builds a kind of Jacob’s Ladder, between the normal, mundane experience of separateness; and the non-dual, fully-integrated experience of enlightenment. It allows you to move up and down this ladder as you wish. Ultimately, the gradual path can only get you so far. Eventually you need to leap “across the abyss.” But it can help pave the way and connect the two endpoints.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="magick" /><summary type="html">There is an ongoing debate between schools that believe that enlightenment happens suddenly; and those who believe it happens gradually, over a long period of study and practice. As is often the case, both are correct, but in different ways. Sudden enlightenment refers to a change in state while gradual enlightenment refers to a change in stage of development. Both are important.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Universe is Black and Empty</title><link href="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/neurophenomenology/2021/05/22/universe.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Universe is Black and Empty" /><published>2021-05-22T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-05-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://www.deeperwisdom.org/neurophenomenology/2021/05/22/universe</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/neurophenomenology/2021/05/22/universe.html">&lt;p&gt;It’s well known that most of matter is empty space. Between the nucleus of an atom and it’s electron shell is a vast void. Even most of the electron shell is empty most of the time. The only reason anything &lt;em&gt;seems&lt;/em&gt; solid is because the electrons at the edge of your skin repel the electrons at the edge of what you “touch”. From a subatomic perspective, nothing ever touches anything (excepting nuclear fusion). It’s like two magnets repelling each other. Think about this the next time you walk across the floor. In a manner of speaking, your feet never really touch the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise with light. Most of space is a black void, with occasional photons flowing through. It doesn’t appear this way because your nervous system did not evolve to represent the world as it is, but rather in a way that would be useful. It fills in the gaps. Everything you experience is an illusion your brain constructs, not to represent the world accurately, but it in a way that is useful. It doesn’t matter whether we are talking about an experience of a predator, of food, or of God. They are all internally generated experiences, extrapolated from some (but really, not much) external sense data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why I like to say, “the universe is black and empty.” I find it to be a useful reminder that my perception is not the world.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="neurophenomenology" /><summary type="html">It’s well known that most of matter is empty space. Between the nucleus of an atom and it’s electron shell is a vast void. Even most of the electron shell is empty most of the time. The only reason anything seems solid is because the electrons at the edge of your skin repel the electrons at the edge of what you “touch”. From a subatomic perspective, nothing ever touches anything (excepting nuclear fusion). It’s like two magnets repelling each other. Think about this the next time you walk across the floor. In a manner of speaking, your feet never really touch the ground.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Ego</title><link href="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/magick/2021/05/21/ego.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Ego" /><published>2021-05-21T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-05-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://www.deeperwisdom.org/magick/2021/05/21/ego</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/magick/2021/05/21/ego.html">&lt;p&gt;There’s a misconception that the ego is bad. The worst thing a spiritual person could be is egoistic. But what is meant by “ego?” The word came into English by way of Freud’s translator. Freud put forth a tripartite model of mind consisting of “the It”, “the I”, and “the Over-I”. To make Freud sound more scholarly, his English translator preferred the Latin: &lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Ego&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Superego&lt;/em&gt;. In Freud’s conception, the “I”, or &lt;em&gt;ego&lt;/em&gt;, is not bad. It’s simply the part you associate with yourself. None of them are bad, though we often treat “the it” as if it were, dissociating ourselves from “it”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if &lt;em&gt;ego&lt;/em&gt; is just the Latin word for “I”, how did it get a bad rap? Spiritual thinkers say the goal is to transcend the &lt;em&gt;ego&lt;/em&gt;. So far as this line of thinking goes, I am in agreement with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, something got lost once it hit the mainstream. The goal of transcending the ego got interpreted to mean the ego is “bad.” This is absurd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s like wings transcending wheels. Once a plane takes off, the wheels are useless. But if a plane didn’t have any wheels, you would be concerned. How will it take off? A plane without wheels can’t take off. Just as we need wheels in order to transcend the need for wheels, so do we need an ego, and a well developed one at that, in order to transcend it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="magick" /><summary type="html">There’s a misconception that the ego is bad. The worst thing a spiritual person could be is egoistic. But what is meant by “ego?” The word came into English by way of Freud’s translator. Freud put forth a tripartite model of mind consisting of “the It”, “the I”, and “the Over-I”. To make Freud sound more scholarly, his English translator preferred the Latin: Id, Ego, and Superego. In Freud’s conception, the “I”, or ego, is not bad. It’s simply the part you associate with yourself. None of them are bad, though we often treat “the it” as if it were, dissociating ourselves from “it”.</summary></entry></feed>