<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.7">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-12-27T09:59:35-08:00</updated><id>https://www.deeperwisdom.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Deeper Wisdom</title><subtitle>Welcome to DeeperWisdom.org  &lt;br /&gt; Stay tuned for resources on the world's wisdom traditions!</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Podcast Is Live</title><link href="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/religion/2020/12/15/podcast-is-live.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Podcast Is Live" /><published>2020-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://www.deeperwisdom.org/religion/2020/12/15/podcast-is-live</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/religion/2020/12/15/podcast-is-live.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-podcast-is-live&quot;&gt;The Podcast is Live!&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Religion of the Month Club podcast is now available on&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/show/42rUsJFYye5XmVVoPyoBFb?nd=1&quot;&gt;Spotify&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/podcasts?feed=aHR0cHM6Ly9hbmNob3IuZm0vcy9hNGEwNzU0L3BvZGNhc3QvcnNz&quot;&gt;Google Podcasts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pca.st/koq1loxp&quot;&gt;Pocket Casts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://radiopublic.com/religion-of-the-month-club-69KoQZ&quot;&gt;RadioPublic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.breaker.audio/religion-of-the-month-club&quot;&gt;Breaker&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/religion-of-the-month-club/id1545073255&quot;&gt;Apple Podcasts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s not much there yet besides a blurb and a brief introduction, but the important thing is: you can now subscribe. So when the first real episode drops in January, you won’t miss it. Stay tuned for more….&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="religion" /><summary type="html">The Podcast is Live!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Religion of the Month Club Podcast is Coming</title><link href="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/religion/2020/11/22/podcast-announce.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Religion of the Month Club Podcast is Coming" /><published>2020-11-22T09:42:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-22T09:42:00-08:00</updated><id>https://www.deeperwisdom.org/religion/2020/11/22/podcast-announce</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/religion/2020/11/22/podcast-announce.html">&lt;p&gt;The first two episodes of &lt;a href=&quot;https://anchor.fm/deeper-wisdom&quot;&gt;the Religion of the Month Club&lt;/a&gt; have been recorded and are scheduled to come out on רֹאשׁ חודש שְׁבָט  (Rosh Chodesh Sh’vat 5781, or January 13) and 農曆新年 (Chinese Lunar New Year, or February 12) respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Episodes will come out on the first of every lunar month as designated by the tradition associated with the text. For the first six months, we will focus on the first chapter of the each text (with some exceptions), &lt;em&gt;e.g.&lt;/em&gt; the first chapter of Genesis (בְּרֵאשִׁית‎), the first chapter of the Tao De Ching (道德經), the first chapter of the Qur’an (القرآن‎), &lt;em&gt;etc.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="religion" /><summary type="html">The first two episodes of the Religion of the Month Club have been recorded and are scheduled to come out on רֹאשׁ חודש שְׁבָט (Rosh Chodesh Sh’vat 5781, or January 13) and 農曆新年 (Chinese Lunar New Year, or February 12) respectively.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Belief and Doubt</title><link href="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/magick/2020/10/20/belief.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Belief and Doubt" /><published>2020-10-20T02:40:50-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-20T02:40:50-07:00</updated><id>https://www.deeperwisdom.org/magick/2020/10/20/belief</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/magick/2020/10/20/belief.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article was originally published in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.weaveandspin.org/cauldron&quot;&gt;The Reclaiming Cauldron&lt;/a&gt; in October, 2020.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;on-belief-and-doubt&quot;&gt;On Belief and Doubt&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things I appreciate about Reclaiming Witchcraft is that it tends to emphasize experience over belief. At the time when Reclaiming was formed, this was not unusual in progressive pagan communities. But over the last few decades, a kind of fundamentalism has crept into many forms of paganism, witchcraft, and so on. When asked, “What about those Humanistic or Atheistic Pagans?” They dismissively reply, “They aren’t.” Just like the fundamentalist Christians they oppose, they mistake dogmatism for authenticity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years, I’ve seen a number of books that seem to take belief as a prerequisite for any kind of magickal practice. Rather than “you need to see it to believe it,” they flip it around and say “you need to believe it to see it.” It’s an interesting idea and one that I myself believed for many years, but I think it’s actually misleading in that it leads one to focus on belief over experience. That isn’t to say that belief doesn’t affect what you experience, it absolutely does. But it’s very difficult, if not impossible, to intentionally change core beliefs; and considering belief (or lack thereof) an obstacle to performing magick is counter-productive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I say I believed that “you need to believe it to see it,” what I mean is that I believed that I &lt;em&gt;needed to believe&lt;/em&gt;. But I didn’t quite believe in magick or the gods. I &lt;em&gt;wanted&lt;/em&gt; to. I wanted to believe they were real. But I couldn’t force myself. I was raised with a scientific mindset and a scientific mindset involves testable hypotheses. If a god exists, you should be able to test for that existence. This led to quite a conundrum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s back up a second and consider this word “belief”. Where did it come from? How did we get so caught up in it? Say I believe that the world is round. I believe there is a beer in the fridge. Whether or not there actually &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a beer in the fridge has nothing to do with whether or not I believe it. The universe doesn’t give a damn about belief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a matter of fact, most religions don’t either. The big exceptions are Christianity and Islam which place a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of emphasis on belief. But historically and globally, those are exceptions. The way in which Christianity dominates theological thought in the Western world could lead you to believe that all religions are about belief. The word “faith” is often conflated with “religion” (more on the distinction between belief and faith below). Attempts at dialogue between members of different religions are called “inter-faith” dialogues. Nevermind that one of those members is a Reform Jew and the other a Theravada Buddhist and neither of them cares much about what their members believe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judaism has been called a religion of “orthopraxis” in order to distinguish it from religions of “orthodoxy” like Christianity. That is to say, what makes a Jew a Jew is what you do, not what you believe. I’d argue that &lt;em&gt;praxis&lt;/em&gt; is more important than &lt;em&gt;doxy&lt;/em&gt; in all religions, not just Judaism, though I admit that’s a somewhat heretical thing to say. Regardless of whether you believe that Christianity is a religion of faith (Romans 3:20) or a religion of works (James 2:24-26), I posit that works come first and faith (but not belief!) comes next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;faith&quot;&gt;Faith&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about faith? Faith, as I understand it, is not really about belief at all. In fact, it is slightly incompatible with belief. As I said, I believe that the world is round. It would seem rather odd for me to say I have “faith” that the world is round. When you believe something, there is no doubt. Belief and doubt are strictly opposed to one another. The degree to which I believe there is a beer in the fridge is directly opposed to how much I doubt there is a beer in the fridge. (And neither of them really matter. All that matters is whether or not there &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a beer in the fridge.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faith, on the other hand, needs doubt. I have no reason to doubt that the earth is round, so it is meaningless to say I have “faith” that the world is round. There is, however, reason to believe that your partner has been un&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration:underline;&quot;&gt;faith&lt;/span&gt;ful. You can’t really know. All you can do is have faith. A friend is faithful because they &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; be otherwise. Faith is more about trust, trust in spite of doubt (or, at least, the possibility of doubt). Faith is often about something you can’t really know the answer to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what I mean when I say “I don’t believe in God but I have faith in God.” That sentence might seem paradoxical, but allow me to unpack it. First, “I don’t believe in God.” I’m a naturalist, I don’t believe in anything supernatural. “God”, in this case, is supernatural. Or perhaps I mean Spinoza’s God, &lt;em&gt;Deus sive Natura&lt;/em&gt;, God/Nature, in which case, again, it is meaningless to say I “believe” in nature. (Maybe not if you’re a mental monist.) So what does it mean to say I have “faith” in this God I don’t believe in? It means I place my trust in some kind of transcendent referent I don’t claim to understand. I understand that there is more to reality than I can comprehend and I am making an unreasonable leap of faith to trust that it is Good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’ve argued you don’t need to believe. Do you need to have faith? No, not really, at least not at first, and maybe not ever. Faith is common to many religions, but not all. Christianity, Islam, Hinduism, and Mahayana Buddhism all involve elements of faith as a path to liberation. And to some extent, that is even true of Judaism and Theravada Buddhism. To say “I take refuge in the Buddha, the Dharma, and the Sangha” is somewhat akin to saying “I place my faith in the Buddha, the Dharma, and the Sangha” (in the way that I mean “faith” here). You can do that whether or not you believe the Buddha was a historical person (or have doubts as to the historical veracity of the many stories told about him). But, unlike Islam, in which placing your faith in God is essence of the whole religion, taking refuge in the three jewels, is just part of it. Being a Buddhist is primarily about the four noble truths and following the eightfold path to liberation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mindfulness movement has shown us that you can get value out of the practices of Buddhism without the trappings of religion. It is, I hope sufficient evidence that practice without belief can be effective. But does this apply only to mindfulness practices? Interestingly, no! It applies to all religious practices. To be a good Jew, you need to keep the Sabbath and the high holy days like Passover and so on. Many of the Jews I know are atheists, or at least agnostic. They are not particularly interested in whether or not God literally appeared as a pillar of fire to guide their ancestors out of Egypt, except perhaps as a fun debate topic after four glasses of wine at the Passover table. What they &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; interested in is practicing their religion, reconnecting with their tradition and with their people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;beyond-belief&quot;&gt;Beyond Belief&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I often say that I learned how to practice divination when I stopped believing in it. In the beginning, I wanted to believe that the cards (or coins or whatever) could really connect me with the patterns of the universe. I guess I do believe that now, but in a very different way than I did then. That is, when I began, I really wanted to believe in some kind of metaphysical (but nonetheless objective) force guiding these symbols. “Wanted” being the operative word there. I didn’t &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; believe, but I thought I needed to in order for it to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I was skeptical, looking for evidence, hoping to prove to myself that it was real, but never quite succeeding. I suppose one thing those books that espouse the importance of belief get right is that you do need to stop doubting, at least while you’re doing it. I stopped doubting when I stopped trying to believe. I stopped doubting when I just tried doing it for fun, when I was at a party with my scientist friends (this was back when I thought I was going to be a scientist) and someone had a tarot deck and just for the fun of it, I offered to give people readings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By then I no longer “believed” in any of this, and I doubt my scientist friends did either. And yet, they were blown away by how “accurate” my readings seemed to be. I put “accurate” in quotes because the accuracy of a divination is almost always psychological. You’re not going to forecast the stock market with Tarot cards (though that hasn’t stopped people from trying). So when a divination is “accurate” it’s not accurate in the same way a weather forecast is accurate. When a divination is accurate, it’s more akin to when a poem or novel resonates with you, when it seems “true” on some deeper level than factual truth. Neil Gaiman once said, “fiction is the lie that tells the truth,” and I think the same could be said for divination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It started off as a parlor trick. I had stopped believing in it but I did not yet have faith in it. But as I practiced for more people and noticed the effect it had on them, I began to have faith in the power of divination, even if I still don’t “believe” in it. I have found the same to be true of ritual magick and the making of talismans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first began the magickal path, I really wanted to believe in it. I thought that if I could just get myself to believe in gods and angels, then I would really see them, really experience them. Then I got to a certain point and realized that if I was going to see them, I would have by now. Eventually, I learned more about how the mind works and I began to doubt it all. Was it all just a game? Were we all just deluding ourselves?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I continued to participate in ceremonies however, for two reasons: 1) it was a social activity I was doing with my friends, and 2) I found it enjoyable. In fact, I quickly discovered that I found it much &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; enjoyable after I let go of belief, or rather, the will to believe. And that’s also, in a way, when the magick really started. Or more accurately, that’s when I became able to appreciate the magick that was already there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The magick was already there. And I felt it from the beginning. But it would pass through my fingertips as I attempted to grasp it looking for some sign that it was really real. When I stopped concerning myself with that, I could just enjoy and appreciate it. Maybe it is all in my head. Probably it is all in my head. (I mean, who knows, maybe there are superdimensional currents of energy that somehow respond to our neural activity during a ritual, but that seems pretty unlikely to me.) But as Lon Milo DuQuette says, “it’s all in your head, you just don’t know how big your head is.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="magick" /><summary type="html">This article was originally published in The Reclaiming Cauldron in October, 2020.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Course: The Golden Dawn and the Western Mystery Tradition</title><link href="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/magick/2020/10/05/gdcourse.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Course: The Golden Dawn and the Western Mystery Tradition" /><published>2020-10-05T07:07:07-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-05T07:07:07-07:00</updated><id>https://www.deeperwisdom.org/magick/2020/10/05/gdcourse</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/magick/2020/10/05/gdcourse.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;course-title-the-golden-dawn-and-the-western-mystery-tradition&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Course Title:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;The Golden Dawn and the Western Mystery Tradition&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Description:&lt;/strong&gt; While the original Order of the Golden Dawn lasted only fifteen years, and ended over a century ago, its influence on what is known broadly as the Western Mystery Tradition, is extraordinarily deep. Indeed, it would be difficult to find an esoteric, magic(k)al, or occult organization in the West that hasn’t been influenced by the Golden Dawn (including and especially the rise of Paganism and other religious movements in the 20th century). Part of the reason for this has to do with the incredible syncretism that appeared in the mysterious cypher manuscripts, weaving together many diverse streams including Hermeticism and Neo-Platonism, Christian and Jewish Kabbalah, ancient Greco-Roman and Egyptian mythologies, Alchemy, Astrology, Theurgy, and Tarot among others. These cypher manuscripts described a system of initiation and education taking the aspirant through five grades in the Outer Order. Later additions added a Portal Grade as well as a series of Inner Order grades. This course will focus on those five original Outer Order grades, exploring their historical context as well as the many layers of symbolism involved in these rituals. While this course does not presume to “initiate” anyone, students who complete the course will have a thorough-going understanding of the methods and symbols involved in the Golden Dawn Order as well as how to apply these teachings to their own spiritual development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For more information, please fill out this form:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;form action=&quot;https://formspree.io/xknpgnql&quot; method=&quot;POST&quot;&gt;
  Name: &lt;input type=&quot;text&quot; name=&quot;name&quot; size=&quot;70&quot; /&gt; 
  &lt;br /&gt;
  Email: &amp;nbsp;&lt;input type=&quot;email&quot; name=&quot;_replyto&quot; size=&quot;70&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;!--br/&gt;
  What is your magic(k)al background (if any)?&lt;textarea name=&quot;background&quot; rows=&quot;10&quot; cols=&quot;70&quot;&gt;&lt;/textarea&gt;
  &lt;br/&gt; 
  What religion(s) (if any) do you identify with/as? &lt;input type=&quot;text&quot; name=&quot;my_religion&quot;&gt;
  &lt;br/&gt; 
  What other religions (if any) do you have familiarity/affinity with? &lt;input type=&quot;text&quot; name=&quot;other_religion&quot;&gt;
  &lt;br/&gt;
  Do you own a Tarot deck? &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; name=&quot;tarot&quot;--&gt;
  &lt;br /&gt;
  Why do you want to take this course?&lt;textarea name=&quot;why&quot; rows=&quot;14&quot; cols=&quot;70&quot;&gt;&lt;/textarea&gt;
  &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;submit&quot; value=&quot;Submit&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/form&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="magick" /><summary type="html">Course Title: The Golden Dawn and the Western Mystery Tradition</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Announcing the Religion of the Month Club!</title><link href="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/religion/2020/07/16/welcome-to-religion.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Announcing the Religion of the Month Club!" /><published>2020-07-16T16:31:30-07:00</published><updated>2020-07-16T16:31:30-07:00</updated><id>https://www.deeperwisdom.org/religion/2020/07/16/welcome-to-religion</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.deeperwisdom.org/religion/2020/07/16/welcome-to-religion.html">&lt;!-- 
&lt;a href=&quot;/categories/#religion&quot;&gt;religion&lt;/a&gt;

 --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming Soon: the &lt;strong&gt;Religion of the Month Club&lt;/strong&gt;, a podcast and discussion group in which we discuss the world’s sacred texts and traditions. Email religion@deeperwisdom.org for more information&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="religion" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>